好的，我很兴奋地介绍下一位演讲者。来，举手看看，
Okay, I'm excited to introduce our next speaker. Show of
这里谁在用Claude代码？
hands, who here uses Claude code?
行，举手看看，谁有代码狂热症？
Okay, show of hands, who here has code psychosis?
来吧朋友们，[清嗓子] 这没什么大不了的。
Come on guys, [clears throat] it's okay.
Come on guys, [clears throat] it's okay. It's Um my
嗯……我的团队开玩笑说我有代码狂热症，
team lovingly says I have Claude code psychosis, which
这可能是真的也可能不是。
may or not be true. we
今天我们有幸请到了Boris Cherny。呃，
are delighted to Boris Cherny with us today. Uh is the creator,
他是代码的创造者、奠基人。在这个过程中，
father of code. and uh in process doing that has just
他亲眼见证了现代软件开发方式的革新。
had a front row seat reinventing modern way software development.
现代软件开发方式。嗯，我们真的很感激您Boris，
modern way of software development. Um and we're really grateful to
今天能抽出时间与我们交流。
you, Boris, for taking the time
我们知道整个开发领域的发展某种程度上都扛在您肩上。所以，
speak with us today. We know that um entirety development kind rests on
感谢您前来。
your shoulders.
今天采访您的是我们团队的Lauren Reader。
So, thank it out be And interviewing is Lauren Reader from our team.
嗯，Aisa你抢了我的开场白。
Um you took my opening line, Asia.
我们问谁在用Claude代码，举手的很多。太棒了。
We asked who here uses Claude code. There's a lot of hands. That's awesome.
感谢您光临Boris，能请到您非常荣幸。嗯，
Thank you for joining us, Boris. It's very special
在座的都是开发者，我认为你们正在彻底改变构建这件事。
to have here. Um as a roomful of builders, I think
所以，我很想探讨一下软件和编码的未来，
are changing building entirely. And so, I'm curious
以及我们应该把空闲时间都花在什么上面。
explore how about the future software, coding, and
我先简单补充点背景，让大家有点概念。
what we should spend all our free
除了创建Claude代码，
time on. but I'll give
Boris是一位真正的工程师中的工程师。
me tiny bit more background on that everyone has
你的整个职业生涯写了大量东西，
little context. So, beyond creating Claude
包括《TypeScript编程》这类教科书。
code, Boris is much an engineer's engineer. You were writing
上次聊天时你说2026年之前几乎一行代码都没写过，
lot through your whole career, textbooks including programming in TypeScript. last
或者说至少到2026年都没怎么写，这变化真不小。
chatted hadn't written single line year, or at least far 2026,
还有个趣事：中学时你为TI-83 Plus计算器写过一篇
which quite change. There's also known thing back middle school, wrote guide uh
BASIC指南。
BASIC TI-83 Plus calculators.
我刚刚搜了一下，它居然还挂在网上。这太尴尬了，
And I just searched for it, it's actually still on the internet.
所以请大家别去搜。[笑声] 但它确实存在。
It's extremely embarrassing, so please don't search it. But [laughter] exists.
我们肯定会把它挖出来的。嗯，我先问几个问题。
We will definitely be finding that. Um we're going to do I'm
也许先聊聊Claude代码的历史，你是怎么开始的，
start with a few questions here. Maybe we'll little bit of history Claude code,
然后留大量时间给观众问答。想着大家心里已经有疑问了，呃，
how you started and then have lot audience Q&A this one. thinking about your in back head,
很快就把时间交给你们。
uh would love turn over all soon.
很快就把时间交给你们。是的。嗯，另外快速问一下，
turn it over to you all soon. Yeah. Um and also
用Claude代码的人，主要是用命令行界面吗？好，
real quick, so for people that use Claude code, do the CLI
大部分是命令行？
mostly? Like okay, majority CLI?
好的。很多啊。大部分是桌面端？
Okay. That's a lot. Majority desktop?
VS代码还是JetBrains集成开发环境？
VS code or JetBrains IDE?
好的。大部分是VS代码或JetBrains IDE？
Okay. Majority VS code or JetBrains IDE? That's actually
其实没有那么多。
not a lot.
好的。其实没有那么多。其他呢？
Okay. That's actually not a lot. Other?
我最近主要用iOS。是的。
I'm like iOS mostly these days. Yeah.
我最近主要用iOS。是的。>> [笑声] 好。酷。
I'm like iOS mostly these days. Yeah. >> [laughter] Okay. Cool.
>> 好。酷。嗯，
>> Okay. Cool. Um
其实我创建Claude代码在很多方面是偶然的。
yeah, so I started Claude code kind of accidentally in a lot ways.
嗯，我在2024年底加入了这支团队。
Um I joined this team back late 2024.
Um I joined this team back in
它当时是Anthropic内部一个叫Labs的孵化器。
late 2024. It was a sort of incubator within Anthropic called Labs.
而呃，这个团队也算是完成了使命。嗯，
And uh the team kind of served its purpose.
我们创建了Claude代码、MCP和桌面应用。
Um we created Claude code, MCP, and desktop app. It was
当时就我们几个人。
a it just few us.
当时就我们几个人。所以，很像一个创新团队。
it was just a few of us. So, very much like innovation team.
我们最终建成了想建的东西，团队解散了——呃，
We built the thing that we wanted to build,
现在团队又重组了，准备第二轮。你应该知道，
disbanded Uh now team's actually back together for round
迈克·克雷格是Anthropic的首席产品官，
two. Mike Krieger, who's you know, chief product officer at
也是Instagram的联合创始人之一，目前由他主导。
Anthropic and used be one of founders Instagram, so he's leading right now.
目前由他主导。嗯，我开始从事编程工作的原因，
that right now. Um so the kind of reason I started to work
是我们觉得存在产品积压。
on coding is we felt like there
我猜在座很多人经常用"积压"这个词——在实验室内部肯定也
was this product overhang. And I'm guessing people here use word a lot. Uh but definitely lot in
常提。
within lab.
实验室内部。有个概念是模型能完成所有事，
of within the lab. Uh there's this idea that model
但还没有产品能实现这一点。2024年底，
can do all stuff no product has yet captured. And
当我们审视编程领域时，当时的最高水平是"提前输入"。
in late 2024, when we were looking at coding, way did state art
你打开IDE，按Tab键，一次只能补全一行代码。
time was type ahead. It you open your IDE and press tab
Sonnet 3.5首次实现了这一点，
like complete one line a time. thing Sonnet 3.5 enabled
但我们感觉还能走得更远——几乎准备好迈出下一步了。所以，
for first But feeling could actually go lot further than that. almost ready next
不用再提前输入了，直接用智能体写代码就行。
big step. So, don't have to ahead anymore, just agent write code.
写代码。于是我构建了它，但前六个月完全不行。效果很不好，
the code. And so, I built it, and just really didn't work for first 6
几乎没法用。我自己写，大概只有10%的代码用它。
months. It was like not very good. barely usable. wrote from used maybe 10%
即使我们最初发布了Claude，反响也并不热烈。
of my code or something that. even after we released Claude initially, a hit.
最初反响并不热烈。很多人用过，
code initially, it was not a hit. There's lot of
但并没有像今天这样的指数级增长。
people that used but did have this exponential growth has today.
今天这样的指数级增长。嗯，从五月的Opus 4开始。
growth that it has today. Um started with Opus 4 in May. And
我记得非常清楚。那时开始呈指数级增长，
I remember very clearly. That's like when the exponential
每次模型发布都拐点上扬。4.5、4.6，现在是4.7，
and then kind of inflected every model release. Uh 4.5, 4.6, now 4.7.
一直在上扬。
It just keeps inflecting.
但本质上，我们试图构建的产品处于产品市场契合前阶段，
But essentially, we were trying to build this thing that was like
而且知道未来六个月都不会达到产品市场契合，
pre-PMF, and knew it wouldn't have PMF for 6 months
因为还要构建下一个模型。这个想法几乎贯穿始终。
because building the next model. And idea pretty much whole time.
几乎贯穿始终。你知道，对Anthropic整体而言，
pretty much the whole time. And you know, for Anthropic in general, we've
我们一直非常专注。
always just been very focused.
我们关心商业和企业安全编程。这就是我们想走的路。所以，
We've cared about business and enterprise safety coding. That's kind of the way that we wanted
在某个节点我们知道要构建一个产品，但不确定具体要什么。
to build. And so, at some point knew build a product. We didn't know exactly what
于是这最终成了产品赌注。
wanted. So, this ended up being product bet.
成了产品赌注。这是个不可思议的故事，尤其是它源于偶然。
being the product bet. It's an incredible story, especially that it was accident.
源于偶然。嗯，你公开说过你认为编程问题已解决。
that it was an accident. Um so, you've said on the record
如果这是Anthropic最擅长的三件事之一，
you think coding is solved. Uh if this one of three best
能否告诉我们更多含义，以及可能仍未解决的部分，
from Anthropic, can tell us more about what mean by and might still
或者会出现哪些二阶问题？好吧，
not be solved, or second-order problems come? All
我换个问题问大家：谁还在100%手写代码？
right. I ask another question for room. Who writes 100% their code hand?
谁在用像Claude Code这样的智能体写100%的代
Who writes 100% of their code using a agent like Claude
码？
code?
好。谁处于中间状态？
Okay. Who's somewhere in between?
谁处于中间状态？所以，大概50%已解决。
Okay. Who's like somewhere in between? So, 50% solved.
所以，大概50%已解决。>> [笑声]
Okay. So, like 50% solved. >> [laughter]
>> 对我来说，基本是100%。Claude的代码库，
>> I mean, for me it's like 100%. Like the Claude
嗯，你知道，它泄露过，所以人们知道。相当简单，
code base, um you know, it leaked, so people know.
就是TypeScript和React。没什么大秘密。
Uh pretty simple. It's just TypeScript and React. there's no big secret.
就是React。没什么大秘密。没有什么真正复杂的。
it's React. Like there's no big secret. There's nothing really complicated. The
我们选择TypeScript和React的原因，
the reason we picked TypeScript and React is very on distribution
是模型的分布性很好。所以，当我们开始构建代码库时，
for model. So, when started, you know, building code base, model was
模型没有今天这么智能，所以语言和框架很重要。如今，
not as intelligent it today, so language framework mattered a lot. Nowadays,
你什么都能写，能掌握没见过的新语言和框架。但那时，
can write whatever, pick up new languages, frameworks hasn't seen. But back
我们想用分布性好的东西。
then, wanted to use something pretty distribution.
用分布性好的东西。正因为如此，
to use something pretty on distribution. Because of
我觉得很早我们就达到了模型能写100%代码的程度。
that, I think fairly early we got the point where model just wrote 100%
对我们来说，这发生在去年十月到十一月左右。
code. And for us, this happened sometime in October, November last year.
所以今天对我来说，模型写了我100%的代码。我自己写，
And so, for me today, you know, like the model writes 100% of my code. I
通常每天提交几十个拉取请求。
write somewhere, usually a few dozen PRs every day.
上周有一天我做了150个——破了纪录。
Uh there was a day last week I did like 150 in That that
我只是想试试看能推进到什么程度。
record. just trying to kind of push see how far can get it.
试试能推进多少吧。嗯，但对我来说，这问题已经解决了。
push to see how far I can get it. Um but yeah, it's like
不过并非所有地方都这样。有些非常大的复杂代码库，
for me just solved. this is not the case everywhere. There's very big
模型还不太擅长那些古怪的语言。而且，在座各位都知道，
complicated code bases. kind of weird languages model's good at yet. and you know,
要达到那种程度，通常得等下一代模型。
as everyone here knows, getting there. Usually answer wait next model.
能跟我们聊聊你的个人工作配置吗？你那天简单提过，
Can you actually tell us about your personal setup? You walked through it the other day.
挺狂野的。
It is pretty wild.
那天提过，确实挺狂野。嗯，
the other day. It is pretty wild.
大概六个月前我在推特上分享过我的个人配置。有意思的是，
Yeah. Um so, I shared my personal setup like 6 months ago or something on Twitter. And
我当时真没觉得这会让任何人惊讶。那就是我写代码的方式。
it it's funny, actually didn't realize that would be surprising for anyone. That was just way coded.
就像我平时写代码那样。 >> [笑声] 但之后又变了，
like the way that I coded. >> [laughter] And it's changed since then.
一直在变。嗯，
It's changed. Um
实际上现在我的大部分工作都是在手机上完成的。
and so, now actually most of my work do from phone.
我的工作都在手机上做。嗯，不知道你们能不能看到这个，
my work I do from phone. Um and so, don't know if like you guys won't be
但左边开着Claude应用，有个小代码标签，
able to see this, but have um the Claude app, open on left-hand side, there's
里面有好几个会话在进行。
little code tab, just a bunch of sessions going.
嗯，你们可能看不清。
Um you probably can't see it.
>> 有多少个会话？
>> How many sessions?
通常大概五到十个会话。然后每个会话里有一堆代理，
Uh usually have like maybe five to 10 sessions. and then the sessions a bunch
所以现在大概有好几百个在运行。
of agents, so I think currently probably few hundred going.
好几百个代理在跑。
hundred agents going. Um usually
通常每天晚上我会有几千个在做更深层的工作。
every night I have like a few thousand that are doing kind of deeper
有一些管理方法。
work. There's ways to manage it.
有一些管理方法。一个是让Claude用一堆子代理来处理
work. There's a few ways to manage it. One is that you ask Claude use bunch of sub-agents do
一堆子代理来做工作。实际上，
bunch of sub-agents to do work.
我发现自己用得越来越多的是循环。
Actually, the thing that I've been finding
就是这个\\}循环，真是太酷了。
myself using more and is loop. So, this \slash} loop, it's just
最简单却最有效。
like coolest thing. It's
就是让Claude用cron定时任务在未来的某个时间点执
simplest works. All it you have Claude use cron schedule a job for some
行，然后重复执行。
point in future, repeat job.
未来的某个时间点，并且是可重复的任务。它可以每分钟、
future, and it's a repeat job. And it can run every minute, 5
每五分钟、每天运行，你想怎么调度都行。
minutes, day, kind of however often you want to schedule it.
到了 [哼] 现在，我有好几十个循环在跑各种事情。
And at [snorts] this point, I have like dozens of
有一个在盯着我的Pull Request，负责修复CI、
loops that are running for stuff. So, one that's babysitting my PRs,
自动变基。另一个在维护
fixing CI, auto-rebasing. another keeps healthy.
另一个在维护CI的健康。
have another one that keeps CI
比如如果有不稳定的测试之类的问题，它就会去修复。嗯，
healthy. So, like if there's a flaky test or whatever, it'll go and
它还会从推特抓取反馈，每30分钟帮我分类整理一下。
fix it. Um I grabs uh feedback from Twitter kind of clusters it
任何时候都有一堆这样的循环在运行。
for me every 30 minutes. just bunch these loops
我觉得循环就是未来的方向。如果你还没试过，强烈推荐试试。
running at any time. sort feel are the future this point. If you haven't experimented
我们还推出了例程，本质一样但跑在服务器上。
with highly recommend And we also launched routines, which is same
就算你合上笔记本电脑，它也在跑。
thing but on server. even close your laptop, going.
它会一直运行。以上就是你的个人配置。跟我们说说，
keeps going. So, that's your personal setup. Tell us about what
你认为未来的团队会是什么样？
you think teams will look like in
你是如何从你做的这些工作中推断出，
the future. How do extrapolate from all work
如何让团队中的每个人都保持前进、理解上下文，
you're doing to keep everyone on team moving forward, understanding context,
或者我们是不是需要放权给更多代理才能让它运转起来？
or we need let go of a lot more agents make it work?
嗯，我觉得吧，做预测很难，但我在这儿，就试着说几个吧。
Um I think so you know, it's like hard to make predictions, but um I'm here I'll try some.
试着说几个。我感觉未来的大趋势是，
try to make some. I feel like the way that things are going
通才型人才会比现在多得多。
is generally there's be a lot more generalists than there today.
现在我们聊通才，基本上指的还是工程师。他们写代码，
And today when we talk about generalists, I think largely we're talking people that are still engineers. So,
但可能算是产品通才，比如既做iOS也做Web服务器。
they're writing code, but maybe kind of product say generalist, it's like a you know, they do iOS and
这都还在工程领域。
web server, for example. That's in engineering.
但我认为，我们会开始越来越多地看到跨领域的通才。
But I think the thing that we're going to start see a lot more of is generalists are cross-disciplinary.
跨领域的通才。就是那些既擅长产品工程、
generalists that are cross-disciplinary. So, this is engineers really
又擅长设计的工程师，或者既懂工程又懂数据科学的人。
good at product engineering, but also great design. Or and data science engineering.
嗯，我不太确定。这其实是我们团队正在出现的一种现象。
Um I don't know. It's it's something that we're starting to see on our
实际上，Claude 代码团队里很多人都是跨学科的通才。
team. So, actually like a lot of people the Claude code team are generalists across disciplines.
我们团队每个人都会写代码。比如工程经理、产品设计师、
Everyone on our team codes. So, like engineering manager, product designers,
数据科学家、财务人员、用户研究员，每个人都在写代码。
data scientist, finance guy, user researcher, every single person writes code.
整个团队都写代码。所以，你看，他们虽然各有专长，
team writes code. And so, you know, like they're specialist in
但现在每个人也都在写代码。
something, but now also everyone's just coding.
我看到有人点头了，但我猜在座各位可能并不觉得这有多意外，
And you know, I'm seeing some nods, but I bet also it's actually not that surprising to people
因为你们的情况也差不多。
in this room cuz you're the same things.
大家都是类似的情况。嗯（清嗓子），
seeing the same things. Um [clears throat] I'll
我再问一个我最喜欢的问题，然后就开放给观众提问。
have one more favorite questions then we'll open up to audience. So,
我们刚才聊了编程正在发生的变化，
we talked a bit about what's changing with
我很好奇在软件或产品领域，你看到了什么趋势？
coding. I'm curious what you see in world of software or products.
嗯，我觉得随着 AI 让写代码的成本下降10倍甚至100
Um I think as we see AI making writing code 10 100x cheaper, what
倍，用软件生产出来的产品价值会发生什么变化？
happens to the value products that are produced with software? Do
我们会不会面临一场SaaS末日？你觉得这会如何发展？
have a SAS apocalypse on our hands? How do you this plays out?
再说一次，你要再做一个预测。
And again, you're going make another prediction.
SaaS末日这个问题是我最喜欢的。
The SAS apocalypse question is my favorite then.
最喜欢的提问。嗯。
favorite question then. Um
我觉得会有两件事发生，而且都不是人们一直在讨论的那种。
I think there's two things that are going to happen and don't either of them is the thing people have been talking about.
第一件事——在座有人听过《Acquired》这个播客吗？
I think one is Is anyone here an acquired listener? Like the podcast?
对，那是最好的播客。
Yeah, it's like the best podcast.
嗯，我前几周还去录了一期《Unplugged》，
Uh I actually got to do a unplugged with them other
感觉就像见到了我的偶像，因为那两位主持人是最棒的。
week and just felt meet my heroes cuz they're hosts are best.
他们是最棒的。他们有个“七种力量”的概念，
are the best. So, they have this idea of uh seven
来自汉密尔顿写的那本关于商业模式的书。
powers and is a like Hamilton. He kind wrote he
我认为随着AI的发展，其中一些力量会变得更重要，
book about modes in business. And I think what's going to happen because
另一些则会弱化。比如，转换成本这种力量会减弱，
AI, some these get more important less important. so, for example, one
因为你可以轻松地把模型从一个东西迁移到另一个东西。
that gets switching costs you can just use model port from thing different thing.
从一件事换到另一件事。另一种会弱化的是流程优势，
from one thing to a different thing. Another that gets less
因为对于那些商业模式依赖工作流之类的公司，
important is process power because for companies whose mode like
Claude已经非常擅长梳理流程了。特别是4.7版本，
workflows and things this, Claude getting really good at figuring out process. And
它可以自动爬山优化任何目标。你只要给一个目标，
especially with 4.7, it can just hill climb anything. So, if
说“迭代直到完成”，它就会照做。
you give target tell iterate until it's done,
我认为这是第一个能做到这点的模型。
will do it. I think the first model that.
是第一个这样的模型。所以我认为这些因素会变得不那么重要，
is the first model like that. So, I think these are going to get
但之前的商业模式其实仍然有效。像网络效应、规模经济、
less important, but previous modes actually still matter. this network effects, uh
稀缺资源这些东西，并不会因为AI而改变。
scale economies, cornered resources, things These not really changing with AI.
我认为第二件事是，看看今天或未来十年内的创业公司数量，
I think the second thing is if you look at number of startups today or like maybe in
那些能够颠覆一切的公司可能会增加10倍。
next know, past 10 years, that are just going to disrupt everything increase 10x.
增加10倍。因为现在你可以是一个很小的创业公司，
increase like 10x. Because right now you can be a tiny
却能打造出和大公司一样有价值的产品，并且直接正面竞争。
startup, could build thing that's as valuable large company and actually compete head-to-head
因为大公司必须调整业务流程、改变工作方式、
because the has to evolve their business process, they have
重新培训所有人使用新技术，它们会面临大量内部阻力。
way work, retrain everyone use technology, they're going face lot of internal resistance that.
但你们在座的人没有这种问题。
resistance to that. But you know, no one here has that problem.
你们都没有这种问题。如果你是从零开始，
you know, no one here has that problem. If you're starting
你可以从一开始就以AI为核心来构建一切。
fresh, then can kind of build with AI natively from the ground up.
所以，我不确定。但我觉得这是最好的创业时代，
So, I don't know. think it's the best time to
也是创业的最好时机。将会有巨大的颠覆来临。
build. It's be a startup. there's so much disruption coming.
这么说来，我们还是有希望的。
So, there is hope for us after all.
这么说来，我们还是有希望的。谢谢你，鲍里斯。
So, there is hope for us after all. Thank you, Boris.
嗯，我很乐意开放观众提问环节，如果有人想问问题的话。
Um I would love to open up audience questions if anyone has anything they like ask.
有人想问问题吗？丹？
would like to ask. Dan?
我，嗯，我很好奇。
I Yeah, I'm curious.
你说在产品市场匹配前六个月就搭建了产品，
Um you said that built uh 6 months before there
但现在模型已经足够好了，
was product market fit, but now
你觉得Claude Code的成功有多少归功于模型本身，
given the models are good enough, how much do attribute success of Claude code
又有多少归功于产品领域的决策？
to model versus like decisions in field product?
产品领域？嗯，我觉得可能是两者相结合。
field of product? Uh I think it's probably a mix.
嗯，我觉得可能是两者相结合。对，如果你一年前问我，
Uh I think it's probably a mix. Yeah, if you asked me maybe year ago,
比例大概是五五开。
the ratio was something like 50/50.
嗯，我不知道。如果你六个月前问我，比例可能还是
Um maybe I don't know. If you asked me 6 months ago, the mix would be
五五开。 >> 那两年后呢？
50/50. >> What about in 2 years?
哦，老兄，我不知道。我们只规划未来一周的事。
Oh, year I don't know, dude. We plan like we 1 week out.
我们只规划未来一周。 >> 几个月？未来的某个时候。
in like we plan 1 week out. >> months. Sometime the future.
>> 几个月？未来的某个时候。[笑声] 顺便说一句，
>> months. Sometime in the future. [laughter] And by way,
我认为之所以是五五开，嗯，你知道，
I think reason it was 50/50 is
就像YC（创业孵化器）早期教的那样。
um you know, like did YC back
作为一家公司的第一个员工，参与过很多初创公司。
day. first hire at a company and bunch of startups.
在初创公司里，他们一直灌输的理念，尤其是YC，
And in startups like the thing that they drill into you and then
就是打造人们喜欢的东西。
especially YC over is build something people love.
所以，产品是什么、模型之类的都不重要。
And so, it doesn't matter what the product is, like model
你最终还是要打造一个人们喜欢的东西。
and all this stuff. You still in end have to
我觉得这就是为什么我们如此关注你日常使用时的小细节，
build a thing that people I think that's why matters we pay much attention little details
这确实是一种很棒的体验。
as you use day, it's really great experience.
我觉得随着模型变得更好，工具层的重要性会降低。
I think as the model's gotten better, harness kind of gets less important.
工具层的重要性会降低。
the harness kind of gets less
我认为我们现在思考的是如何改进工具层？
important. And I think like that we're thinking about right now
比如让循环操作成为更核心的功能？
is how do we evolve harness? So, make loops more
如何让运行多个智能体更简单？嗯，你知道，
a first class thing? How it easier to run lot agents? Uh you
子智能体是个想法。
know, beside sub agents one idea.
对，子智能体是一个想法。我们还在酝酿更多的东西。
know, like sub agents is one idea. There's a bunch more stuff that we're cooking.
但我认为一年后，模型的对齐能力会好得多。
But I think in a year, the model will be much
所以我们今天所有的安全机制，比如提示注入防护、
better aligned. And so, all safety mechanisms that we have today around uh
静态验证命令、权限模式、人工介入循环等等，
prompt injection and kind of static verification commands permission modes, human loop,
都会变得不那么重要，因为模型会做正确的事。
this stuff is just going to less important cuz do right thing.
会做正确的事。嗯，这就是我的预测。
do the right thing. Um So, yeah, that's my prediction.
你想扔一下盒子吗，丹？ >> [喷鼻声]
You want to toss the box, Dan? >> [snorts]
>> 太好了。嗯，如果从软件层面稍微拉远一点来看，
>> Great. Um To zoom to out a little bit
我觉得 Claude 代码在几个月前带来了一种文化变革，
from software, I think Claude code did cultural change few months
它让构建软件这件事变得大众化了。
ago where it democratized like building software.
你可以看到店铺老板为自己编写软件，甚至用编程控制单片机，
You can see uh shop owners their own um software for themselves or even programming microcontrollers
在有人开门时自动开关灯。
to control the light when someone opens door.
嗯，你认为未来构建软件会不会成为像“我会用 Micros
Um do you see in future um building software becoming a skill like
oft Office”这样的通用技能？
uh I know Microsoft Office? so, it's thing that
变成每个人都能掌握的东西，而不仅仅是科技行业的人？
ev- everybody can not just people tech industry? Oh my god, yes.
哦天哪，当然会。我觉得甚至还不止于此。
Yes. think going to be even more than that. don't
就像现在谁都会发短信一样。
know. It's yeah, how send text message.
我觉得，嗯，你知道的，
I think um you know,
我阅读的两大主题基本就是科幻和技术史。
like read a my two genres are essentially sci-fi and
这是我大量阅读的内容。
tech history. This is what lot of.
技术史。这是我最常读的东西。在技术史中，
history. This is what I read a lot of. think in
有一个在我看来与当下正在发生的事情最为清晰的类比。
tech history, there's one thing which to me the clearest parallel for what's happening
那就是15世纪欧洲的印刷术。
right now. And this 1400s, printing press Europe.
欧洲的印刷术。在当时，大约只有10%的欧洲人口识字。
the printing press in Europe. And what happened was before essentially 10% of European population literate. They knew
他们懂得读写。
how to read and write.
这些人通常受雇于国王和不识字的领主。
They were often employed by like kings lords that not literate.
以及那些不识字的领主。他们的工作就是读写，
and lords that were not literate. And their job was to you know,
而这是当时人尽皆知的事情。
read write this is something everyone knew how do.
>> [轻笑声] 印刷术被发明之后，又出现了两台印刷机。
>> [snorts] The printing press was invented, then there were two
在第一部文学作品出版后的50年内，
more presses and in the 50 years
欧洲的文献数量比之前的一千年还要多。
after first literature published Europe than thousand before.
而在同一时期，
And over the
文献的成本——一本书的价格下降了大约100倍。然后，
same period, cost of literature, a book went down like 100x.
你知道的，这又花了几百年时间，因为学习读写本身很难。
then, you know, it took couple hundred years cuz learning to
你需要建立教育体系、需要政府推动、
read and write is hard. You need
不能让所有人都还在农场干活等等。但接下来的几个世纪里，
education systems government everyone can't be working on farms so on. But
全球识字率上升到了70%。现在我们所有人都能读写，
next few literacy globally up 70%. now we can all don't degree
不需要专门拿个读写学位。
in reading writing how write.
尽管仍然有专业的写作者在做这件事。
Although still there are professional writers that thing do.
这是每个人都能够做的事。所以，我认为同样的事情即将发生，
is a thing that you can do. So, I think the that's about to happen
而且会比50年快得多——软件将被彻底普及，任何人
and it's going be much faster than 50 years software will fully democratized, anyone
都能做。而且，你知道的，这有很多推论。比如，
can do. And you know, there's a lot of corollaries to this. So, for
假设你在编写会计软件。
example, let's say you're writing accounting software.
我认为，编写会计软件的最佳人选，甚至可能到今天为止，
The best person to write accounting software, I think maybe even
都不是工程师，而是一位真正优秀的会计师，
today, is not an engineer, it's a really good
因为他们对领域非常熟悉，而编码反而是简单的部分。
accountant because they know the domain well and coding easy part.
非常熟悉，编码反而是简单的部分。真正难的是了解这个领域。
really well and coding is the easy part. It's knowing domain that's hard And
而我认为这显然就是未来。
I think this just obviously future.
所以，嗯，Greg 说过的一点是，
So, uh one of the things Greg said
你们某种程度上已经生活在未来了，
was that you guys are living in
因为你们能够使用模型和智能体。
future a little bit cuz get to
Claude 代码在发布之前曾是一个内部工具。嗯，
have access models and agents. Claude code an internal tool before released
工程领域和外部世界之间的差距是一个月吗？还是三个月？
it. Um is gap between where engineering rest world, month? Is it 3 months?
世界，是一个月吗？还是三个月？六个月？
world, is that a month? Is it 3 months? 6
而这个差距是在变大还是在变小？
And gap getting bigger or smaller over time?
是的，实际上在内部，我们使用的是和外部所有人一样的模型。
Yeah, so internally, we use the same models everyone else does.
嗯，对我们来说，
Um for us,
内部试用（dog fooding）非常重要。
the dog fooding is really important. So, we
所以我们用这些东西，你知道的，
use thing that here you know,
比如先小范围试用一下 mythos，
like a little bit of mythos to
然后大量用 Opus 4.7 来编写我们大部分的代码。
try it and then lot Opus 4.7 food write most our code.
我们的代码。嗯，我认为在模型层面，其实没有什么差距。
of our code. Um I think on the model side, there isn't
你知道的，就像 mythos 一样，
really a gap. you know, it's like pretty
它最终会以某个版本的后代形式在某个时间点向所有人开放。
much mythos and that will become some version descendant available at point to everyone.
在某个时间点向所有人开放。我认为在产品层面，
available at some point to everyone. I think
差距可能要大得多。而这只是因为我们在改变我们所有的流程。
on the product side, there's probably a far larger gap.
如果你和 Anthropic 的人聊天，
And that's just related us changing all
你会发现我们实际上什么都用 Claude。
of our processes. Like if you talk
Claude 们整天都在对话——就像我在编码时，
people Anthropic, we use Claude for literally everything. Claudes
我的内循环中，
are talking
它们会通过 Slack 和其他人的 Claude 交流，
day like as I'm coding, my in loop, they will communicate
而那些 Claude 也在运行，去弄清楚一些未知的东西。
over Slack other people's that also running kind figure out unknowns.
我们公司现在没有任何地方再手写代码了。
We have no more manually written code anywhere
所有SQL都由模型生成。所有东西都是自动构建的。
at the company. All of SQL is by uh models. Everything
所以我认为，实际上我们领先的地方并不是技术，
just built So, I think actually place that we're ahead
因为同样的工具对所有人来说都是可用的，
not technology cuz same available to us everyone here
核心在于我们正在构建一个平台。因此，
because fundamentally, we are building a platform. And
开发人员能够用上我们推出的所有东西，并且亲自试用，
so, for it's really important developers can use thing using and dog
这一点非常重要。
food everything put out there.
我们推出的所有东西。但我认为，在组织结构和流程方面，
everything that we put out there. But I think there's actually a far bigger weed
其实有一个更大的问题。而这就是一个地方，
in kind of the organizational structure and process. And this is place
希望大家可以在这里讨论，让每个人都能学习并共同进步。
where you know, hopefully can talk about it places like uh everyone learn from also evolve.
并共同进步。是的，我认为这就是初创公司的一个优势。
and also evolve. Yeah, I think that's one of the advantages startups have. It's
从零开始要容易得多。
so much easier to start there.
是的，嗯，上次我们聊的时候，
Yeah, um last time we talked,
我记得你提到了一点关于多代理的内容，
I think you'd mentioned a little bit about
而且在之前红杉的活动上，你说有一些事情正在推进中，
multi-agent and it was very in code at the prior Sequoia event
是你正在考虑的东西。现在显然有了/slash批处理、
you that there were some things going down pipeline thing you're talking
循环、子团队、团队。你能谈谈是在模型层面还是框架层面，
thinking about. Now obviously there's slash batch, loop, sub teams, teams. Can speak
如何通过注入先验知识和目标函数，来改善这种委派任务、
to either model level harness how injecting priors objective function is changing kind
启动代理的体验吗？因为很多事情是可以并行处理的。
of make this experience around delegating work, spinning up agents better? Cuz
你可以做得更快，感觉我需要靠直觉来判断什么时候并行，
so much parallelizable. You can do many faster feel like have overlay my
而不是理解如何启动10个代理来处理某件事。
own intuition for when parallelize rather than understanding spin 10 something.
可以为某件事启动10个子代理。是的，从产品角度来看，
can spin up 10 sub agents for something. Yeah, I mean on the product side,
这其实归结为提示工程。
it really just comes down to prompting.
就是这样。所以，你知道，我们调整提示词，
That's how it is. And so, you know, we tweak prompts kind
帮助模型更并行地处理事情。
of help the model do stuff in parallel more.
但说实话，随着模型变得更好，它自然会这样做。
But also, honestly, as the model gets better, it
所以像循环这样的功能，
just naturally does this.
我发现实际上4.7版本就开始做到了。这真的很酷。嗯，
And so, something like loop, I found actually 4.7, starts doing.
我会告诉它：“去拉取这个数据查询。”它就会说：“嘿，
Uh which is really cool. It's uh you know, I'll tell
注意到这个数据随时间变化。开始一个循环，
"Go pull this data query." it's "Hey, noticed
每30分钟给我一份报告。”我说：“太好了。
that changing over time. start a and give report
能发到我的Slack上吗？
every 30 minutes." I'm "Great.
”然后它就用Slack MCP做到了。所以我认为，
Can send to me Slack?" then uses Slack MCP do that.
未来用户不用再费心去想如何更好地使用工具了。如果是这样，
So, think time, not on users figure out how hold tools better. if
那就是产品设计的问题，要做好。
that's case, product design problem doing good job.
而且好像我做得并不好。实际上，
and like I'm not doing a good
这要依靠模型本身更好地处理这些事，
job. It's really on the model to do
我们只需要给它合适的提示，它自然就能做到。
this stuff better us kind of prompting it so naturally does this.
嗯，所以现在，
Um so, right
我们很多人似乎都在用Claude或Codex这些云端工具
now it seems like a lot of us use um Claude or Codex these uh
来进行计算。但也有人非常强烈主张让AI本地化。
tools in the cloud to do our computing. But then, there are some
我可以想象，随着时间的推移，
very vocal advocates having your AI be local.
随着开源模型和其他技术的发展，
And I could imagine over time as open
人们获得高质量编程辅助的可能性会更大。所以，
way models and other things catch up that this more possibility for
我很好奇你未来几年的愿景是什么。
people get really high-quality coding assistance. So, I'm curious
你觉得整个趋势是大家仍然依赖集中式计算，
vision say next years something that. Do you see trajectory everyone still
还是会转向我们都有本地代理，不用担心被限速，
relying on centralized compute is pivot oh, we all just have local agents
还能享受其他好处？
can rely they don't throttled benefits?
以及其他好处？是的，我觉得这个……不知道。
and other benefits? Yeah, I think it um don't know. There's maybe a
可能有几种回答方式。最基本的一种是，这根本不重要。
few ways to answer that. like kind of the most fundamental way that is doesn't matter.
回答是，这根本不重要。因为我认为现在我们正到达一个点，
answer that is it doesn't matter. Cuz I think now we're getting to the
模型能够自己搞定了。所以，再过几年，
point where model just able figure out. So, like by
模型将包揽所有代码工作。它会启动代理，构建环境。
a couple years from going be doing all code. It's starting agents. building environments.
它会自己去构建环境。所以，如果它决定用本地模型来做，
going to be building the environments. And so, like if it decides actually I'll use local models do this,
那它就会这么做。
then you know, that's what it'll do.
那它就会这么做。我认为这些将不再是工程师需要做的决策了。
then you know, that's what it'll do. These I don't think these will be decisions that we are making as engineers anymore.
我们还有时间再问几个问题，所以我可以抛出这个问题。
We have time for a couple more questions, so I can toss this out.
问题，所以我可以抛出这个问题。杰米。
questions, so I can toss this out. Jamie.
内斯特。谢谢。
Nester. Thank you.
感觉Claude Code一个很厉害的决定，
It feels like one of the great uh decisions with Claude
是利用了许多开发者的工具和工作流都是本地化这一事实。
Code was making use fact that a lot developers' tools and workflows are local.
但对于一般的知识工作来说，情况不一定是这样，
But um that isn't necessarily always the case for
很多人用的是云端工具。我很好奇，
sort of general knowledge work with,
你们是如何思考Co-work这个产品的，
you know, cloud tools. I'm curious how you're
它能否像Claude Code对开发者那样，
thinking about this Co-work do give enough access to
为我们使用的工具提供足够的访问权限，让它同样强大？
tools we use be powerful same way Claude Code is developers?
就像Code对开发者那样吗？是的，这是个非常好的问题。
Code is for developers? Yeah, it's That's a really great question. Um
嗯，我知道当我在大公司的时候，
I know when was uh at big
我们花了大概5年时间把所有环境迁移到远端。
company, we took like 5 years moving all the environments
这工作量太大了，尤其是在大规模下。
to remote. It's just so much work, especially scale.
尤其是在大规模下。嗯，但对于知识工作来说，
especially at a big scale. Um but for
它其实已经存在了，
knowledge work, largely, it's
比如Salesforce和文档这类工具。
there already with like Salesforce and Docs things that.
文档之类的。呃，对我们来说，
Docs and things like that. Um for
答案往往最简单——就是 MCP。
us, it's always just the simplest answer. It's MCP.
答案就是 MCP。所以，
answer. It's just MCP.
你在 Claude AI 里用的那个 MCP 连接器，
So, the same MCP connector that you have in
接上 Salesforce、Google 文档、
Claude AI, hook up like, know, Salesforce, Google
日历什么的，然后 Co-work 就能用上它。
Docs, Calendar. Uh and then Co-work can use
命令行操作，随处编码。
that. CLI it. Code everywhere
对于那些没有 MCP 的系统，
And for the systems that don't have MCPs,
你觉得这是不是意味着“计算机使用”会成为一个大机会？
like do you think that's where computer use is going to be a big opportunity?
没错，我觉得“计算机使用”算是一个万能方案。呃，
Yeah, I think computer use is kind of a catchall.
目前据我所知，Anthropic 在这方面挺领先的。
Um so, currently, for as far know, Anthropic like pretty ahead
如果你通过 Co-work 来运行，效果相当不错。
on computers. And if you it through Co-work, it's quite
基本上能操控你电脑上的任何软件。虽然现在速度还挺慢，
good. able to much any piece software that have your computer.
但表现已经很好，尤其是搭配 4.7 版本。
It's very slow, but does well now, especially with 4.7.
嗯，但除此之外，我觉得 MCP 基本上就是答案了。你看，
Um Yeah, but I think otherwise like MCP is kind of the answer.
这些杂七杂八的东西其实没那么重要。可以是 MCP、
It's And you know, all this stuff just doesn't matter that
API，或者某种程序化访问方式，
much. It could be MCPs, APIs, some
因为模型只关心这个——它只认 Token。
sort programmatic access cuz model care. to mo- To it's tokens.
说到底就是 Token。好了，我们还能再问一个问题。
it's just tokens. All right, we have time for one more question.
Sean，你要不要抛个——谢谢。
Sean, do you want to toss the Thank you.
Sean，你要不要抛个——谢谢。呃，
你刚才已经暗示过这一点，
Um you've kind of alluded this,
但如果早些时候看到“概率性产品遗留问题”，
but if like sometime ago saw probabil- product overhang and
想着先搭个东西，
thought build a that
等模型变强之后它会变得更有意思——你能不能大概聊聊，
would then become more interesting once models got better, could just talk even
你觉得从现在起半年到一年后，
in vague terms about shape you'd today
什么样的东西会变得特别有价值？
think becomes much as get 6 months year?
半年到一年后会变得更好？嗯，
better in 6 months to a year?
Claude 设计就是个很好的例子。它现在已经挺不错了，
Yeah, Claude design I think is really good example. It's uh it's pretty today.
但还会变得更好。
going get lot better.
呃，还有一些我们正在为 Claude Code 开发的东
Um there's also a few things that we're cooking up for Claude Code uh are
西，未来几周就会上线。到时候你们就能看到了。
going to be landing over the coming weeks. So, you'll see those.
然后，我觉得像这种循环批处理、大规模并行化智能体的事情，
Um and then I think uh loop batch things like this around massively parallelizing agents,
也会变得越来越好。
that's going to get better.
“计算机使用”也是一个很好的例子。
And computer use is another good one.
“计算机使用”也是一个很好的例子。好了，Boris，
And computer use is another good one. All right, Boris. Thank you so
非常感谢你来做客。我们还会在这儿待一会儿，
much for joining us. I think we'll be here a
如果大家还有问题的话。
little longer if anyone has questions.